<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<component type="desktop">
    <id>fi.csc.Elmer</id>
    <launchable type="desktop-id">fi.csc.Elmer.desktop</launchable>
    <name>Elmer</name>
    <summary>Free and open source multiphysical simulation software</summary>
    <metadata_license>CC0-1.0</metadata_license>
    <project_license>LGPL-2.0-only</project_license>
    <description>
        <p>
            Elmer is computational tool for multi-physics problems. Elmer includes
            physical models of fluid dynamics, structural mechanics, electromagnetics,
            heat transfer and acoustics, for example. These are described by partial
            differential equations which Elmer solves by the Finite Element Method (FEM).
        </p>
    </description>
    <url type="homepage">https://www.csc.fi/web/elmer</url>
    <url type="help">https://www.csc.fi/web/elmer/documentation</url>
    <url type="bugtracker">https://github.com/ElmerCSC/elmerfem/issues</url>
    <developer id="fi.csc">
        <name>CSC – IT Center for Science Ltd.</name>
    </developer>
    <screenshots>
        <screenshot type="default">
            <image>https://raw.githubusercontent.com/ElmerCSC/elmerfem-manuals/18525101b6d6ef8951f641329482f19866d8277f/latex-elmergui/images/elmergui.png</image>
            <caption>Main ElmerGUI window</caption>
        </screenshot>
    </screenshots>
    <content_rating type="oars-1.1"/>
    <releases>
        <release version="26.2.1" date="2026-04-29">
            <description>
                <p>Elmer FEM 26.2.1 brings a new ADIOS2-based output solver, expanded solver capabilities, library and finite-element improvements, bug fixes, and updates across ElmerGrid, ElmerGUI, and Elmer/Ice.</p>
                <p>Highlights:</p>
                <ul>
                    <li>New ADIOS2OutputSolver for compact parallel output in ADIOS2/BP5 format, including Fides JSON export for Paraview.</li>
                    <li>Enhancements to EMPort, MarchingODE, and CalcFields solvers, including improved port handling, eigenmode sorting, automatic shifting, timestep subdivision, multiple components, and nodal Lorenz force support.</li>
                    <li>Finite element updates such as alternative second-order Nedelec bases, a third-order triangular H(curl) basis, new tetrahedral quadrature, and prism element fixes and support.</li>
                    <li>Mesh and integration improvements, including binary mesh read/write support, temporal splitting for step-function integration, broader H(curl) Dirichlet support, and new Gauss point namespace options.</li>
                    <li>Bug fixes for XML timestep formatting, passive interfaces, adaptive integration, mortar projectors, restart handling, MATC locale handling, halo initialization, and quadratic H(curl) approximation.</li>
                    <li>ElmerGrid now supports binary mesh writing and element type 718; ElmerGUI adds tentative support for element type 718.</li>
                    <li>Elmer/Ice gains grounding-line flux computation in 3D extruded simulations, GroundedMask and LimitedSolution initialization fixes, passive element fixes, and related test updates.</li>
                    <li>Continuous integration and testing received many improvements, and some obsolete mortar projector code was removed.</li>
                </ul>
            </description>
        </release>
        <release version="9.0" date="2020-11-11">
            <description>
                <p>New features:</p>
                    <ul>
                    <li>New vectorized and threaded Navier-Stokes solver with block preconditioning</li>
                    <li>Beam element module to complete structural models</li>
                    <li>Mixed element Poisson solver (with Hdiv basis)</li>
                    <li>Large number of improvements for electromagnetics</li>
                    <li>Coupled structural problems enables (e.g. shell-solid)</li>
                    <li>Enable automatic elimination of conforming BCs</li>
                    <li>Faster and improved view factor computation</li>
                    <li>Better support for parametrized runs with Run Control and inline parameters</li>
                    <li>And more!</li>
                </ul>
            </description>
        </release>
   </releases>
</component>
